on to chapter two the low road to octave
inference so all chapters begin with a
short quotation and the quotation here
reads my thinking is first and last and
always for the sake of my doing William
James so even before reading the chapter
these quotations are often great places
to jump off and have a discussion so Ali
please begin and go as long as you want
on the low road to active inference
okay
so uh yes
chapter two uh as the title suggests
it's the construction of active
inference Theory from the Viewpoint of
of the low road active inference So It
Begins by uh providing this notion of
perception as inference because uh more
often than not we usually think of
perception as something uh just in a
computational sense of the sense is the
processing of the of the inputs or
rather it's the raw processing of the
inputs but here it shows that it can
also be described as or even more
accurately described as a kind of
inference so it's not just a simple and
raw
processing of the inputs as my a
computational model uh
or a computer analogy might suggest it's
more
um like uh something that we predict and
then
um then we compare our inputs or the
inputs we get from the stimuli uh with
our prediction and then try to somehow
minimize that prediction error so I
believe that this notion of perception
is inference is uh the most Central
notion of all the related theories of
predictive coding predictive processing
Bayesian brain hypothesis so up to now
active inference uh is not very
different from all the other theories
it's basically a subset or a variant of
those theories but then it progresses uh
into uh distinguishing uh distinguishing
the active active inference from all the
other theories and how uh it stands
apart from the other ones
uh so uh in section 2.1
uh we began with some of the basics of
probability Theory namely the base
theorem uh in box 2.1 uh and uh some
simple examples uh about how base
theorem can be applied
uh and again a very important uh page or
important part of this section will be
page 20 which describes the concept of
surprisal and specifically the
statistical surprisal and how it differs
from the phenomenological surprise or
psychological surprise uh so uh and
that's how we can formulate the
statistical surprise yes yes just just
to catch up here this example that's
going to come back again and again is a
person who's guessing the object that's
in their hand and it could be a frog or
an apple and the object is going to jump
or not and so that's used as a way to
talk about the Bayesian updating that
forms the kernel of a variety of
Bayesian brain like models including
active inference
and then
um there are the presentation of the
exact base so in simple cases you can
compute exactly what you want with Bayes
theorem however it's a lot more
effective on large data sets to use
certain approximations and heuristics
that we're going to be discussing
and then
um Ali has highlighted that there are
two concepts that are very closely
related to each other regarding surprise
there's Surprise by itself and then
there's Bayesian surprise so please pick
up there what are surprise and Bayesian
surprise and why do they matter here
yes so um well surprise I mean the
regular surprise as we're all familiar
with uh is something
um more related to our sense of surprise
or psychological sense of surprise of uh
observing some unexpected phenomena or
unexpected Behavior but based in
surprise or statistical surprise uh is
the of course closely related with the
psychological sense of surprise but a
bit more rigorous in which it's a way to
compare to
um probabilistic information using a
callback Library Divergence and
somehow getting the I mean how
unexpected that information
emerging from callback Divergence uh and
uh they call it the surprisal so uh
surprisal is uh you know in other words
is a way to formulating those unexpected
uh probabilistic information and it
doesn't necessarily uh align or maps
onto perfectly are psychological sense
of surprisal but as I said it's closely
related with that
I know I was just gonna say that
um
I was just gonna say that by surprise
um almost in the rest all the
um other sections and chapters of the
book uh we basically mean this Bayesian
surprise uh sense of the world and in
order to distinguish that with
the regular uh sense of surprise uh
sometimes in the literature surprisal is
used to refer to Bayesian surprise
yes so they're both measured in
information theoretic units this is all
happening in information geometric
spaces the first concepts of surprise is
applied to a given single observations
how surprising is that one observation
and so in that sense it's a lot like the
z-score of a data point coming in with
respect to a statistical distribution so
it's like you have a height distribution
in a classroom and you measure one
person and then you can say what is the
z-score of that measurement was it right
at the center of the distribution with
the z-score of zero or with a two
standard deviations higher with a
z-score of two so it's kind of like that
and that's why there's a discussion of
probability distributions and their
support which is the X values for which
they're defined and surprise function
with the fancy I and that's going to be
a function that helps you compute how
surprising each observation is given a
parameter as of that distribution
whereas this Bayesian surprise
is more related to learning it has to do
with how much updating happens between
the prior and the posterior and that's
before and after the observation so one
could imagine a surprising observation
surprise concept one that either does or
doesn't update the prior into a very
different posterior so as Ali mentioned
they are not exactly the same but it's
going to be important to understand how
they're different and that's worked out
again in the case of the Apple jumping
box 2.2 continues with a discussion of
expectations now expectation in everyday
parlance might be specifically referring
to something in the future like I expect
it to rain tomorrow
and in statistics when we talk about the
expectation we're talking about the
weighted average or the center of
gravity of a distribution and that can
be in both a discrete distribution at
which point you have a weighted sum or a
continuous distribution in which case
it's an integral so you can have an
expectation for the humidity tomorrow
and so that might refer to the center of
gravity at A T equals plus one but just
taking a loan expectation means center
of gravity of a statistical distribution
not anticipation
section 2.3 is going to describe how
some of this how this low road that
we're on is going to connect to
biological inference
there's uh more discussion of the
generative model and the generative
process
and a little bit of a hint that the
generative model captures aspects of the
generative process which is where we see
a lot of the classical cybernetic
theorems and Concepts like requisite
diversity good regulator theorem and so
on however the generative model does not
have to be exactly isomorphic with the
generative process for example
degenerative process the temperature in
the room might be a continuous variable
but then the generative model might be
discrete only modeling integer based
temperatures or might be categorical
like too hot just right and too cold so
there's a lot of articulations that can
be done because of how flexible and
interoperable generative models are with
each other
figure 2.2 is going to expand upon that
chapter 1 representation of the
cybernetic action perception Loop and
we're going to see this more in terms of
a generative model and generative
process articulation and there are
incoming speaking from the perspective
of the generative model the agent
they're incoming and outgoing
dependencies in this graph and this is a
little bit like a schema more so than a
formal graph but also it is like a
Bayesian graph where nodes are variables
and edges are causal relationships and
so we have the internal states of the
model
the external states of the generative
process and then the blanket states that
make internal and external States
conditionally independent and again
speaking from the perspective of the
agent although there is a symmetry we
can talk about the incoming sensory
signals
happening from the observations handed
from the process passed on to the
internal states of the generative model
and then the outgoing actions that are
selected that then can influence the
hidden state of the world for example
going and turning on the heater to
increase the temperature in the room
and so this action perception Loop or
particular partition is going to get
explored in a lot more detail in the
coming sections
previous section 2.3 was on perception
as inference and now action as inference
is going to be discussed and that is
where they say the discussion to this
point is common to all Bayesian brain
theories
we now introduce the simple but
fundamental Advance offered by octave
inference which is the extension of this
inferential perspective to consideration
of action as inference
perception action cooperate to realize a
single objective
section 2.5 is about minimizing the
discrepancy between the model and the
world we already described that there's
two ways for this to happen change your
mind and change the world that's how the
discrepancy can be reduced or managed
we see a variant of the action
perception Loop where the agent is
making perceptions uh predictive
models of the world
that through perception are being
juxtaposed with observations handed from
the generative process the world and a
discrepancy is realized some non-zero
discrepancy
and then here are those two paths to
minimize free energy change beliefs by
perception and learning or change the
world through action
section 2.6 is going to discuss how the
exact Bayesian approach described
earlier is absolutely spot on if you
have infinite Computing resources
however we're often interested in Rapid
or large data sets where we want to be
able to get approximate Bayesian
computation or probably approximately
correct computation in a vastly
accelerated fashion and so that is going
to be approached using what's called
variational Bayesian inference that's
unpacked in chapter four
but it suffices to say that variational
Bayesian inference implies substituting
two intractable quantities
the posterior probability and log model
evidence
with two quantities that approximate
them but can be computed efficiently the
approximate posterior q and a
variational free energy so it transforms
an intractable estimation problem into a
highly tractable optimization problem
pick up from there Ali
uh yes but sorry I just wanted to point
out out a couple of things especially
about section 2.3 because I believe it
is um one of the crucial sections of
this chapter and in fact the whole book
because uh it provides some of the
justifications of using uh Bayesian
inference uh as opposed to as some other
uh
mathematical techniques such as maximum
likelihood estimation but
more important than that I think it's
this concept of optimality which comes
into play in almost everywhere in the
literature and of course in this book so
there are actually two Notions of
optimality uh which is not discussed in
detail here namely Bayesian optimality
and Jane's optimality but uh some in
some of the recent papers and Bayesian
mechanics uh Dalton's active at
development and others have shown that
those two concepts of optimality are
actually congruent with each other so
that's one of the reasons
that the Duality between
fep free energy principle and
constrained maximum entropy principle
um
I can
I mean it's one of the justifications
for uh providing that dual formalism
between those two uh so uh but another
point I wanted to mention here is
because I've seen that using uh the word
hidden State uh can be a bit confusing
for some people because uh when we
observe uh something as an observation
obviously it is not quote-unquote hidden
right so what a hidden State here refers
to is actually the hidden cause of that
observation so it's not that the
observation itself is hidden from the
observational or it's unobserved so that
might be a bit uh confusing if if we
don't take into consideration the exact
meaning of the Hidden state or latent
State here and in the rest of the
literature
so continuing from section 2.6 uh here
we see uh one of the two Central
equations of active inference which is
equation 2.5
for variational free energy so
it's as I said I mean understanding this
equation and how each line of its
formulation represents in terms of the
uh I mean trade-off between energy
entropy or complexity inaccuracy or
Divergence and evidence
is key to understanding almost
everything in the rest of the book and
in many other literature on active
inference so
this is the perceptual part of active
inference so variation free energy
is a parameter that uh
uh is a notion that parameterizes the
surprisal of our perceptual information
we have about the external States
and then we'll see in the next section
uh the related and almost symmetrical
formulation to variation of free energy
namely expected free energy which is
basically the action part of the active
inference so we can see how those two uh
can somehow uh be seen as a kind of
unified formalism but described in the
alternate
Expressions so but another thing about
equation 2.5 is uh it it may be a bit
um I don't know daunting to see all the
relations between those three lines of
equation and how we can get from one to
the to the other so there are some
supplementary materials that we have
developed in the past weeks
which I think can help in clarifying how
the derivative nations of these three
lines of equation be done so I hope they
would be clarifying in I mean and helps
to understand how those three lines
relate to each other
uh so
but the key Point here is uh
to understand the variation of free
energy is not something uh absolute but
it's just an upper Bound for the
minimization so as Daniel just mentioned
it's uh untractable to have an absolute
amount for the surprisal to be minimized
so we need to have an upper Bound in
order to make that more tractable
because uh by Jane's inequality as we'll
saw in
um we chapter four I think
we can see that how the upper bound of
the surprisal uh
necessarily provides a condition for
minimizing the precise or the exact
um free the exact free energy
and that's the key Insight of equation
2.5 or the notion of variation of free
energy which is to provide this upper
bound instead of the exact amount of
surprises to be minimized
yeah what I'll what I'll add there is if
you knew exactly how well you should be
surprised by a given data point why then
you would have had the optimal model
however that is not tractable and so by
making a quantity that's always higher
or an upper bound the variational free
energy F which is a function of broadly
Q our beliefs or variational beliefs
which are built in a way that makes them
very compositional very optimizable very
interpretable and data
and we can reduce the Divergence here
are the KL diversions with a double line
between Q our beliefs and P the kind of
actuality of it and if we can reduce
this Divergence in other words minimize
the free energy then we will come closer
and closer to the true surprise function
and do that in an attractable
incrementally optimizable way so
equation 2.5 is going to be the
variational free energy different ways
that it can be represented as it takes
in data and beliefs about the world Q
and then this is going to be expanded
into the future to include action with G
the expected free energy
now there's a lot more that we can say
about this there's a lot of
technicalities to go into but broadly
notice that g the expected free energy
is a functional of policy Pi because
it's only being evaluated to select
amongst different action outcomes pi and
another important difference is that
it's going to be describing sensory
outcomes that haven't yet happened a
sort of what would I perceive if I did a
or what if I did B and it's that kind of
comparison that allows the expected free
energy functional here
to be used in action selection or policy
selection as inference planning as
inference
that section is expanded upon
and in figure 2.6 we see a very nice
representation of the expected free
energy equation and then how when
certain aspects of this equation or
situation are zeroed out we get certain
other familiar cases for example
where there's no epistemic value there's
no information to learn then you get
ruthless expected utility Theory and
conversely where there is no pragmatic
value to extract so all outcomes are
equally valid for or preferable then you
get things like Infomax principle and
optimal Bayesian design and then
everything in between is the space that
we're interested in and so this figure
2.6 shows that the expected free energy
functional can be seen as like a
generalization of a lot of other
settings related to perception and
action and planning amidst uncertainty
and section 2.9 closes the low road they
took us all the way to active inference
from Bayes theorem through the
generative model onto active inference
and clarifies these two Notions of
variational free energy that's the
real-time perceptual unfolding evidence
lower bound on surprisal tractable
optimizable and so on and f and g the
expected free energy which is able to do
planning as inference or policy
selection as inference expected free
energy is fundamentally prospective
and that enables counter factual
cognition
section 2.10 summarizes active inference
is the theory of how living artifacts
underwrite their existence by minimizing
surprise or attractable proxy to
surprise variational free energy via
perception and action and they motivate
that from a first principles base
theorem starting place
any closing thoughts on chapter 2 Ali
I would just humbly suggest for the
people I want to go through this chapter
to
try try their best to really understand
uh specifically what equation 2.5 and
2.6 represents and how uh I mean how to
use those equations to describe
different
situations with some missing elements as
well because I believe those sections
and particularly those equations are
absolutely essential to for
understanding uh everything active in
prints related both in this the rest of
this book and uh in the rest of the and
in almost all
thanks in just the last thought I'll
give on chapter two is this is exactly
the work that we do in the active
inference textbook group we really
welcome all backgrounds every single
question and uncertainty you have is
beautiful we have a lot of resources
that Ali and others make to make the
math approachable and rigorous
and natural language descriptions of the
equations and so on so yes it's really
important to understand the equations
because after all that's like the
skeleton that gives meaning to our usage
and fluency of the active inference
ontology which Ali and I are speaking
right now
we're not just saying surprise is
related to this because we felt it that
way it there is an underpinning and it
is a really interesting life's work to
explore it but we're finding ways to
communicate it and learn and teach it
better and better every time
so that's chapter two that's the low
road